[Music]
[Applause]
after september 11th i became the chief
of counter-terrorism operations in
pakistan
i was told on my first day to come up
with the standard operating procedure
for taking down a terrorist safe house
so i literally sat at a desk with a
legal pad
thinking well how how am i going to do
this what would what would be the first
thing i i would want to do if i was
going to take down a safe house well i
would want it to be dark
so let's say two o'clock in the morning
we'll do it so i wrote o200 at the top
of the page and then little by little i
came up with this plan
finally we got
a report from headquarters that abu
zubaydah was somewhere in pakistan now
at the time we thought that abu zubaydah
was the third ranking person in al qaeda
and all we knew was that he was
somewhere in pakistan but pakistan is
the size of texas
he made one mistake that allowed us
to narrow his location down to 14
different sites
so we brought in a large team from
headquarters half cia half fbi we
brought in weapons and electronics and
walkie-talkies and we hit all 14 sites
at exactly the same
time
and he happened to be in one of the
houses
he tried to escape by jumping from the
roof of his house to the roof of the
neighboring house and the pakistanis
shot him three times in the stomach the
groin and the thigh and he was very
gravely wounded
he was out of it for
a day and a half before he finally came
out of a coma but i was the first person
to speak to him
at first he asked for a glass of red
wine
and then a couple hours later he asked
me to smother him with a pillow
once he sort of had his bearings and he
realized oh my god the americans have me
he wanted to
know what was going to happen to him
where he was going to be sent he was he
was very frightened
um i think of of the unknown
i didn't know where he was going to go
and i didn't know that he was going to
be tortured i didn't have a need to know
[Music]
he would recite poetry to me that he had
written
[Music]
he cried at the thought of he said never
knowing the joy of fatherhood never
knowing the touch of a woman
i remember telling him
i should hate you and i should want to
kill you and i don't
i said you're pathetic
i mean he was just a young guy he wasn't
even 30 years old and all he did was cry
and i remember saying to a colleague of
mine
this
is the fearsome al-qaeda this is what
we've been so worried about and so
frightened of it was a revelation to me
they're just guys they're just and not
even that they're just young illiterate
guys
that had nothing else to do and believe
me when i say 99 of them had never read
the quran
they weren't true believers they they
hadn't pledged fealty to osama bin laden
they just wanted to get out of that
village in yemen and maybe make a couple
of bucks
it made me think the mission wasn't all
it was cracked up to be
and then a colleague came in and said
headquarters is sending in a private jet
to pick him up and take him to his next
location
at about three o'clock in the morning we
wheeled him out he was so upset he asked
me to hold his hand
he asked if we were going to kill him
and i said no
no we've been looking for you for a long
time
in fact i said you're going to get the
best medical care that the us government
has to offer
and so the doctor gave him a shot of
demerol and it knocked him out and we
loaded him onto this private jet
one of the guys who had flown out to
escort him to his onward location got
off the plane the guy was dressed
completely in black black mask black hat
black sweater
and he said my name he said john
and i said who are you and he lifted up
his mask and he was a former supervisor
of mine in headquarters and he said what
are you doing here and i said oh i'm
chief of counterterrorism i said what
are you doing here he said i'm gonna
take your prisoner onward
he said who is he anyway
and i said i'm sorry man you don't have
a need to know
and i said where are you taking him
and
the guy said i'm sorry man you don't
have a need to know
and i said well safe flight
and
the plane took off and i never saw him
again
when i returned to headquarters from
pakistan
i was told that the cia had begun a
program that they were calling enhanced
interrogation techniques
and did i want to be trained in the use
of these enhanced interrogation
techniques uh
i had a visceral problem with it
first of all let's call it what it is
it's torture they can they can call it
whatever euphemism they want but it's
torture
so i went back to the counterterrorist
center and i said i have a problem with
this and i don't want to be involved
and then i heard rumors that we had
created this system of secret prisons
around the world
that even the heads of state in these
countries didn't know that we had these
secret prisons there that these were
deals struck between the head of the cia
and the head of whatever that country's
service was
these weren't meant to be permanent
facilities they were just meant to
extract information
where we didn't have to worry about laws
or human rights
but you know those of us who weren't
read into these programs only got this
in bits and pieces
i had no idea how extensive the secret
prison system was until a couple of
years after i left the agency and i read
about in the press
because we're americans and we're better
than that
but at the time you didn't feel that way
at the time i was so angry
and i wanted so much
to help disrupt future attacks on the
united states that i felt it was the
only thing we could do
and with zebedee you think that was
successful it was i had been misinformed
by the cia
the cia told those of us in headquarters
that they had waterboarded abu zubaydah
one time that he had cracked and that he
had provided actionable intelligence he
answered every question just like i'm
sitting here speaking to you so in your
view the waterboarding broke him i think
it did yes and did it make a difference
in terms of it did the threat
information that he provided disrupted
a number of attacks maybe dozens of
attacks that turned out to be untrue
and we know it was untrue because in
2009 the cia inspector general's report
was released indicating that abazo beta
had been waterboarded 83 times
and still did not provide actionable
intelligence
believe me for the life of me i wish i
could take that back
but
i talked
about the issue with the information
that i had at the time
and the information was just simply
incorrect
abbas abu zubaydah may never have been
an al qaeda member now in retrospect
we're finding out he may have been
somebody who supported al qaeda's goals
he may have been someone who was a
professional logistician where he was
helping them procure
medicine or false documents we don't
really know but he was not the senior al
qaeda official that
the cia and nsa and the white house
wanted us to believe